Finding Aid for Willow Run Area Recreation Project records, 1942-1945
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Willow Run Area Recreation Project records 1942-1945
Willow Run Area Recreation Project.
0.5 linear ft.
88217 Br 2
Agency established to develop recreational and community organizations in the Willow Run, Michigan, area as a means of improving home-front morale during World War II. Subject files relating to Project activities; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the First Unitarian-Universalist Church of Ann Arbor (donor no. 5319 ).
The record group is open to research.
In 1942, metropolitan Detroit became one of America's major war production centers. One community whose population greatly expanded with the migration of defense workers was Ypsilanti, site of the Ford Willow Run bomber complex. Nearly half of the area's 36,000 aviation plant workers were crowded into the several neighborhoods of Ypsilanti. Housing was often inadequate, public utilities were strained beyond limits, and social services for many citizens were practically non-existent.
Efforts to improve home-front morale resulted in the Office of Community War Services creating social and recreational planning agencies throughout the country. The Willow Run Area Recreation Project was one of these agencies and its staff developed dozens of community programs between 1943 and 1945: tenant committees, neighborhood associations, recreation centers, hobby clubs, service societies, religious fellowships, sports tournaments, adult education programs, and consumer co-operatives.
This record group documents the development of the Willow Run Area Recreation Project with emphasis on several programs supported by the staff. Approximately half of the folders contain material that relate directly to the Project goals, staff, and finances. In addition, there are two files, the Detroit-Area Recreation Committee and the Civilian Defense Agency, that contain material relevant to the efforts of the Willow Run Project. Of particular note within the General Information file and Survey file are several summary reports. Each contains excellent overviews of the Project goals and accomplishments. There are also a number of statistical sheets concerning the population of the Ypsilanti community.
Within the remaining folders are documents from specific programs coordinated by the Willow Run Project staff. Several folders contain newsletters and support material for consumer cooperatives. Other folders outline recreational activities and social services such as daycare centers for children of working parents. There is also a small file of publicity photos.
Subjects:
Willow Run (Mich.); World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Children.; Children's parties.; Willow Run Area Recreation Project (Mich.); Willow Run (Mich.); Women.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Topical files
  - Child Care Committee, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Civilian Defense Agency (Recreation), 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Community Centers, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - Cooperative League Bulletins (Box 1)
  - Cooperatives (East Michigan-Central States), 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Cooperatives (Ypsilanti Progressive), 1944 (Box 1)
  - Cooperatives (Norwayne), 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Cooperative Recreation, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Council of Churches (Box 1)
  - Detroit-Area Coordinating Committee, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - General Information (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings and events flyers (Box 1)
  - Publicity Photographs (Box 1)
  - Staff (Box 1)
  - Survey Material (Box 1)
  - Willow Court Newsletter, July-August 1943 (Box 1)
  - Willow Court Tenants Association, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Willow Run Community Council (Box 1)
  - Willow Run Health Agencies (Box 1)